Samarcand Manor School Records SR.5899
State Archives of North Carolina
Samarcand Manor School Records
1915-2011
SR.5899
5899
7.50
Department of Crime Control and Public Safety
Department of Public Safety
State Archives of North Carolina
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Reports
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Reports and Student Newsletters
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: MacNaughton, Robeson and Mitchell Administration
Box Samarcand Manor School Records:Mitchell Administration and Print Materials
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Division of Youth Services
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Photographs
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Slides and Negatives
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Administrative Binder 1
Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Administrative Binder 2
Box RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor School Records: Manuscript Originals
Box RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor School Records: Photographs
Item RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor Gift Log
Item RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor Scrapbook
Item RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor Visitors Log
Folder Samarcand Manor Oversized House Photos
Folder RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor Oversize Photos
Folder RESTRICTED Samarcand Manor Blueprints
Technical Access
Slides and negatives in this series may require advance notice for access due to technical requirements. Please consult the reference staff for more information.
Access Restriction
This record group contains records restricted under public records law, General Statute 7B-3100. Records that expose the identity of juvenile offenders are restricted in access to the juvenile, their attorney, parent or guardian or by order of the court.
Where possible, redacted copies of these records have been made available and are denoted as such with "Contains redacted copies of records restricted under GS 7B-3100" on the folder.
Biographical/Historical
The State Home and Industrial School for Girls, otherwise known as Samarcand Manor, was established in Eagle Springs in Moore County by the state of North Carolina in 1918 under the jurisdiction of the State Board of Charities and Public Welfare. Originally, the home was intended to address what was perceived to be a problem of loose and immoral women, known as "camp followers," who surrounded the troops training for WWI. The intention of the institution was to provided separation and rehabilitation, especially of the many juvenile girls.
With the enactment of juvenile court laws in 1919, the school worked toward focusing on and accepting only juvenile offenders who passed through the court system. During this time period, Samarcand housed girls and women from the ages of 5 to 30. Samarcand became a juvenile-only facility once the adult offenders were moved to the newly established Farm Colony for women in 1927. During this time period, the child welfare system also developed a foster care system for the very young, and Samarcand came to house only adolescents from the ages of 10 to 16. Samarcand remained a girls-only institution through its first three superintendents: Agnes McNaughton (1918-1934), Grace Robeson (1934-1944), Reva Mitchell (1944-1973).
In 1943, the institution was placed under the jurisdiction of the Board of Correction and Training, which later became the Department of Juvenile Corrections and by 1971 was the Division of Youth Services. This division originated under Corrections but was later placed under Human Resources. Later, juvenile services were returned to the jurisdiction of the Department of Crime Control and Public Safety. At some point under the jurisdiction of Human Resources, the school went coed and began accepting both male and female students. In 2002, it reverted to a female-only facility. Samarcand Manor closed in 2011, and the site is now used as a training facility for corrections and law enforcement officers.
Department of Public Safety
Scope and Content
Samarcand Manor Record Group contains records pertaining to Samarcand Manor, originally the State Home and Industrial School for Girls, from 1915 to 2011. The records include administration materials such as correspondence, policies, procedures, handbooks, reference print materials, Board Meeting materials, reports, and grand jury investigations. It also contains academic materials such as curriculum, memorandum, student assessments, housing records, and student newsletters as well as memorabilia such as graduation announcements, programs, photographs, and other ephemera. This record group contains records restricted under public records law, General Statute 7B-3100. Records that expose the identity of juvenile offenders are restricted in access to the juvenile, their attorney, parent, or guardian or by order of the court.
There are seven boxes of manuscript materials and two boxes of photographs and slides available to the public. There are five boxes of restricted manuscript records, photographs, negatives, and slides. Six scrapbooks and seven visitor and gift logs are also restricted. Redacted copies of restricted records are included in the open manuscript records when possible.
The record group contains the following series: Reports (1925-1980); Student Newsletters (1922-1991); McNaughton Administration (1915-1933); Robeson Administration (1934-1944); Mitchell Administration (1944-1973); Reference Print Materials (1920 - 1973); Division of Youth Services (1976-2011); Photographs, Negatives, and Slides (1920-circa 2011); Administrative Binders (1935-1944); and Restricted Records.
- Reports, 1925 - 1980; SR.5899.1; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety
  - Biennial Reports of Samarcand Manor, 1928-1956; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Biennial Reports of Samarcand Manor)
  - Biennial Reports of Samarcand Manor, 1928, 1938 and 1944; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Biennial Reports of Samarcand Manor)
  - Biennial Reports of NC Board of Juvenile Correction cotaining Samarcand Manor, 1968-1972; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Biennial Reports of NC Board of Juvenile Correction cotaining Samarcand Manor)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1925-1926; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1928; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1927-1929; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1930; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1931; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1932; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1933; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1934; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1935; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1934-1936; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1936; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1937; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1937-1939; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1938; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1939; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1940; SR.5899.001; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1941; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1942; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1943; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1943-1945; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1944; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Internal Reports, 1955-1956; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Internal Reports)
  - Samarcand Youth Service Status Report, 1978-1979; SR.5899.002; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Youth Service Status Report)
  - Samarcand Situation Analysis, 1980; SR.5899.002; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Situation Analysis)
  - North Carolina Board of Charities and Public Welfare Biennial Report, 1932-1934; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder North Carolina Board of Charities and Public Welfare Biennial Report)
  - Other NC Juvenile School Reports, 1925-1943; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Other NC Juvenile School Reports)
- Student Newsletters, 1922 - 1991; SR.5899.2; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety
  - Samarcand Manor "Pine Burr" and "Communique", 1922 - 1971 and 1991; SR.5899.002; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Samarcand Manor "Pine Burr" and "Communique")
  - Other NC Juvenile School Student Newsletters: Eastern Carolina, Stonewall Jackson and Morrison Training Schools, 1944-1955; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Other NC Juvenile School Student Newsletters: Eastern Carolina, Stonewall Jackson and Morrison Training Schools)
  - Out of State Student Newsletters, 1934; SR.5899.002; Department of Public Safety (Folder Out of State Student Newsletters)
- McNaughton Administration, 1915 - 1933; SR.5899.3; Department of Public Safety
  - MacNaughton Administration: Marienfield Open Air School for Boy, 1915-1916; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration: Marienfield Open Air School for Boy)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Correspondence, 1918; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Correspondence)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Programs, 1922; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Programs)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Other Institutions Forms, Policies, 1920s; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Other Institutions Forms, Policies)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Parole for Women and Girls, Correspondence, 1924-1925; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Parole for Women and Girls, Correspondence)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Dedication of Chapel, 1928; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Dedication of Chapel)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Student Government Reference Materials and Reports, 1930-1933; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Student Government Reference Materials and Reports)
  - MacNaughton Administration:Qualifications of a Superintendent by Kate Burr Johnson, 1932; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder MacNaughton Administration:Qualifications of a Superintendent by Kate Burr Johnson)
- Robeson Administration, 1934 - 1944; SR.5899.4; Department of Public Safety
  - Robeson Administration: Board Meetting Materials, 1937-1939; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Board Meetting Materials)
  - Robeson Administration: Correspondence, 1934-1944; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Correspondence)
  - Robeson Administration: Curriculum and Academic Materials, undated; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Curriculum and Academic Materials)
  - Robeson Administration: Policies, Procedures and History, 1934-1941; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Policies, Procedures and History)
  - Robeson Administration: Appropriations Granted by the General Assembly, Report of Osborne, 1943; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Appropriations Granted by the General Assembly, Report of Osborne)
  - Robeson Administration: Reference Materials, 1934-1944; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Reference Materials)
  - Robeson Administration: Chronological History and Recommendation for Sterilization, 1935; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Chronological History and Recommendation for Sterilization)
  - Robeson Administration: Information Regarding Admission of Native American Girls, 1938; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Information Regarding Admission of Native American Girls)
  - Robeson Administration: Memorabelia, 1935-1943; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Robeson Administration: Memorabelia)
- Mitchell Administration, 1944 - 1973; SR.5899.5; Department of Public Safety
  - Mitchell Administration: Correspondence, 1945-1949; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Correspondence)
  - Mitchell Administration: Meetings, Conferences and Lists, 1946-1948 and undated; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Meetings, Conferences and Lists)
  - Mitchell Administration: Curriculum and Housing, 1944-1949; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Curriculum and Housing)
  - Mitchell Administration: Samarkand Behavior Code and Revision, undated; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Samarkand Behavior Code and Revision)
  - Mitchell Administration: Private Papers, 1944-1975; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Private Papers)
  - Mitchell Administration: Graduation, 1950-1966; SR.5899.003; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Graduation)
  - Mitchell Administration: Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration, 1968; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration)
  - Mitchell Administration: Memorabelia, 1944-1975; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Mitchell Administration: Memorabelia)
- Reference Print Materials, 1920 - 1973; SR.5899.6; Department of Public Safety
  - Reference and Print Materials: MacNaughton and Robeson Administration, 1920-1942; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Reference and Print Materials: MacNaughton and Robeson Administration)
  - Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 1), 1944-1973; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 1))
  - Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 2), 1944-1973; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 2))
  - Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 3), 1944-1973; SR.5899.004; Department of Public Safety (Folder Reference and Print Materials: Mitchell Administration (folder 3))
- Division of Youth Services, 1976 - 2011; SR.5899.7; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety
  - Division and Youth Services: Accreditation, Conference and Meetings, 1988-1991; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Accreditation, Conference and Meetings)
  - Division and Youth Services: Handbook for Teachers, 1982-1983; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Handbook for Teachers)
  - Division and Youth Services: Presentation Materials, 1999 - 2010; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Presentation Materials)
  - Division and Youth Services: Work Schedules, Notes and Memoranda, 1976-1980; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Work Schedules, Notes and Memoranda)
  - Division and Youth Services: Student Life, 1980-2009; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Student Life)
  - Division and Youth Services: Graduation, 2009-2010; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Graduation)
  - Division and Youth Services: Third Golf Tournemant, 1990-1992; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Third Golf Tournemant)
  - Division and Youth Services: History of the Division of Youth Services, 1981; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: History of the Division of Youth Services)
  - Division and Youth Services: Print Materials, 1979-2011; SR.5899.005; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Division and Youth Services: Print Materials)
- Photographs, Slides and Negatives, 1920 - Circa 2011; SR.5899.8; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety
  Technical Access
  Slides and negatives in this series may require advance notice for access due to technical requirements. Please consult the reference staff for more information.
  - Photo Album 1: Faculty and Events, 1980-1982; SR.5899.006; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 1: Faculty and Events)
  - Photo Album 2: Staff Portrait, Circa 1920 - 1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Staff Portrait)
  - Photo Album 2: School Buildings, Circa 1920 - 1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: School Buildings)
  - Photo Album 2: Field, Circa 1920 - 1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Field)
  - Photo Album 2: Reva Mitchell, Superintendent, Circa 1944 - 1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Reva Mitchell, Superintendent)
  - Photo Album 2: Ada Tobitt, Budget Office, Acting Superintendent, 1933-1934; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Ada Tobitt, Budget Office, Acting Superintendent)
  - Photo Album 2: Grace Robson, Superintendent, Circa 1934-1944; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Grace Robson, Superintendent)
  - Photo Album 2: Mrs. J. R. Page, Member of Board of Directors, Circa 1920 - 1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Mrs. J. R. Page, Member of Board of Directors)
  - Photo Album 2: Agnes MacNaughton, Superintendent, Circa 1920 - 1933; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 2: Agnes MacNaughton, Superintendent)
  - Photo Album 3: Buildings, Landscapes and Staff, 1918-1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 3: Buildings, Landscapes and Staff)
  - Photo Album 4: Samuel E. Leonard, Commissioner of Corrections, 1943-1956; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 4: Samuel E. Leonard, Commissioner of Corrections)
  - Photo Album 4: Blaine M. Madison, Commissioner of Corrections, 1956-1972; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 4: Blaine M. Madison, Commissioner of Corrections)
  - Photo Album 4: William R. Wendley, Youth Services Division Chief, circa 1977; SR.5899.006; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 4: William R. Wendley, Youth Services Division Chief)
  - Photo Album 4: NC Governors Hodges, Sanford, Holshauser, Hunt and Martin, circa 1954-1993; SR.5899.006; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 4: NC Governors Hodges, Sanford, Holshauser, Hunt and Martin)
  - Photo Album 4: Buildings, circa 1920-1950; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photo Album 4: Buildings)
  - Photos: Gallery Frame: Samarcand Manor Bluebird Trail Photos, 2003; SR.5899.006; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Folder Photos: Gallery Frame: Samarcand Manor Bluebird Trail Photos)
  - Photos: Morrison Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Morrison Hall)
  - Photos: Ireland Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Ireland Hall)
  - Photos: Administration Building, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Administration Building)
  - Photos: Classrooms, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Classrooms)
  - Photos: Caroll Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Caroll Hall)
  - Photos: McGeachy Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: McGeachy Hall)
  - Photos: Bickett Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Bickett Hall)
  - Photos: Page Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Page Hall)
  - Photos: Chapel of the Cross, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Chapel of the Cross)
  - Photos: Hope Chamberlain Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Hope Chamberlain Hall)
  - Photos: Miscellaneous Buildings, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Miscellaneous Buildings)
  - Photos: First School Building, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: First School Building)
  - Photos: Tufts Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Tufts Hall)
  - Photos: The Little Manor, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: The Little Manor)
  - Photos: Gardner Hall, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Gardner Hall)
  - Photos: Farm, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Farm)
  - Photos: Landscapes, Nature, Animals and Livestock, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Landscapes, Nature, Animals and Livestock)
  - Photos: Miscellaneous Staff, Adults and Administrators, Pre 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Miscellaneous Staff, Adults and Administrators)
  - Photos: Juvenile Commission and Miscellaneous Adminstration Photos, Post 1960; SR.5899.006; Department of Public Safety (Folder Photos: Juvenile Commission and Miscellaneous Adminstration Photos)
  - Samarcand Manor School Records: Slides and Negatives, Circa 1920-1990; SR.5899.007; Department of Crime Control and Public Safety (Box Samarcand Manor School Records: Slides and Negatives)
  - Samarcand Manor House Photos, Circa 1920s-circa 1940s; SR.5899.010; Department of Public Safety
- Administrative Binders, 1935 - 1944; SR.5899.9; Department of Public Safety
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 1, 1934; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 1)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Loose Front Materials, 1935-1954; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Loose Front Materials)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 2, 1934; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 2)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 3, 1935-1936; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 3)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 4, 1935; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 4)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 5, 1936; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 5)
  - Administrative Binder 1: Page 6, 1936; SR.5899.008; Department of Public Safety (Folder Administrative Binder 1: Page 6)